Okay. Well, hello, class.
So this lecture is going
to now continue the
investigation of Dr.
Sutherland's work by now moving
on to the cranial concept
or what's been called
appropriately, I think,
osteopathy in the cranial field.
The reason I think that
is appropriate is because
Dr. Sutherland considered
his concept an expansion
of osteopathy. So as
we work through today's
lecture, I do hope I can
help you understand that
concept and how it developed
or arose, and then what
exactly the concept entails,
what are the different
components or what I
like to call phenomenon,
because a phenomenon is
something that is observed.
And then we will go into
detail about each of
those components or
phenomenon, as well as looking
at the overall movement
of the cranium called
inhalation,
exhalation, with each
part having its own
motion. And then
as we look at components,
trying to understand
their function and some of
the anatomy around them.
Okay, so we looked at this last
time with the BLT
lecture with Dr.
Sutherland actually
attending school when it was
basically mostly an
apprenticeship, you know, after
still had people who taught
anatomy and physiology
and, and some of that kind
of aspect of the training,
but the clinical training
was under him. And there
was a lot of hand over
hand teaching, which is
still, I think, really
important, you know, as you go
through the labs to try
and make sure that I know
it's a little crazy and we
don't have enough instructors
to appropriately guide
these types of labs, but
at least once or twice
across the lab, have someone
just really get their
hands over yours so you can
feel things. And then
that lineage or tradition
continued, at least in my
experience with Dr. Wales.
She was part of his
faculty for 10 years and
basically a lifetime
student of his work.
I had the chance to
work with her. And so
I guess in my mind,
that's why I'm at
least qualified to
talk to you about this.
so Dr. Sutherland time
and time again discussed
this as essentially Dr.
Still's concept you know if
you really read the writings
of Dr. Still carefully
even between the lines
you'll find that his thinking
was along these same
lines the lines of the
cranial concept you will
find that the cranial concept
in the science of osteopathy
was his, not mine.
And then this one, which
you know, we hope that
you may understand how the
cranial concept became a
contribution of thought
in a otherwise unexplored
area or channel of
osteopathy, a thought that
is in no way apart from
the science of osteopathy.
Get that nothing apart.
Not a specialty by itself,
not even a therapy. We
are dealing with a science.
Osteopathy is a science.
So I guess I bring this up
because you know the first
question, oh are you going
to do cranial? And the
answer is no. I'm going
to I practice osteopathy.
And yes, my treatment will
include the head. And if
it's a head injury, or
even maybe a headache, that
may be a really important
part of my treatment. But
I'm going to evaluate the
head and treat it in someone
who's got a backache, or
asthma, or is post-op.
As osteopaths, if you
really want to practice
right, you do an overall
evaluation and then
design your treatment
plan. And we'll talk
about that more as I
look at some of the
systemic work and try to
put all this together.
Dr. Wales was quite
simple about it. Dr.
Sutherland helped me complete
the osteopathic concept
by adding the head to
the rest of the body.
So as we explore the
cranial concept, I'm going
to bring up some of the
concepts from BLT. And
in some ways, I think
you can understand where
they came from, because
I think some of them came
out of Dr. Sutherland's
study of the cranium,
particularly the concepts
of involuntary motion.
So Dr. Sutherland had
that thought while he
was in Dr. Still's
school So Dr. Still, you
know, that osteopathic
tenet of structure and
function are interrelated
I'm sure you've heard
it and you've kind of
spit it back at times
You know, Dr. Still
taught that you study
structure for the purpose
of understanding function
And if you look closely
and insightfully at
how something is built
and designed, you really
can come to an understanding
of how it works.
And so the day came when Dr.
Still was studying a skull.
It was like this. It's
called the Bouchane skull,
and it's a disarticulated
skull set up on a stand so you
can see the relations of the
parts. And he was thinking,
you know, well, study
structure and look at function.
So he was looking at this
area in here. This is the
parietal bone. This is the
temporal bone. Here's the
sphenoid bone. And he was
looking in that area there.
And the thought struck him,
this is a design for motion.
Now, of course, even at
that time, any anatomist
who was teaching taught
there was no motion in the
head. You still see that
in the anatomy text today.
I'll talk about that a
little bit later on when we
look at the movement of
the bones in particular.
um and so when he looked
at that he thought boy
that's uh beveling is the the
the shape of the articular
surfaces um and how
they're carved out they're
beveled like the gills of
a fish so uh you can you
can sort of see that um
this is uh these are fish
gills and and look at that
beveling it's just the
same so you know gills
have to move in order to
function for the um for the
fish to sort of breathe.
And so it designed
for motion for a
respiratory function
or mechanism.
And that thought he could
not get out of his head.
Everything he read said,
well, there is no motion
there. Everything is fused.
And so he, in his own
words, you know, went on
to try and disprove that,
this idea that that really
was a design for motion.
and that there was motion
in the head. Of course,
that study ultimately
showed him that there, in
fact, was motion in the
head. He would look at
specimens. He was able to
take adult skulls and pull
apart. I mean, you look
at that Bouchain skull.
Those sutures were not
fused. If they were, it would
have just shattered as
they expanded it with rice
or whatever. Or instead,
it comes apart at those
sutures because they don't
really fuse and ossify.
And then, you know, he
went on to study and he
thought, well, I can't
really practice on my
patients or investigate
or experiment on them,
essentially. So he did
it on himself, and he
designed all these torture
devices, essentially.
This is one here with the
pads in the middle, and
this helmet where he takes
straps and apply them
in such a way to twist his
head into every possible
different strain pattern
that he could think of.
And in doing so,
you know, he a couple of times
put himself in the hospital.
And of course, there was
no one to get him out of
it because what's he going
to say? Can you treat
my head? I put a strain
in there and then they're
going to think he's
nuts. And even if they
didn't, nobody knows how
to how to treat that stuff.
So he had to find his own
way out, which he came
to appreciate the incredible
importance of that.
In a statement, he says
here, I had to gain
knowledge of many
things in order to prove
that motion between
the cranial bones is
essentially possible. Had
I tried them on another
person, I would have
only had information.
They would have had
the knowledge. So
when something happens
to you, when you
have that experience,
that's knowledge.
When you hear about
it or read about it
or study it in a book,
that's information.
And knowledge is always
better. So the take home
is, you know, we're all
tired and come into lab and
you lay down and someone's
going to work on you
and you just want to relax
and kind of float into
that nice relaxing space.
And I would say, you know,
you're missing half the
education. Pay attention
when you're on the table.
Even, you know, one of
the hardest parts about
learning to palpate the
cranial mechanism, cranial
motion, is the contact,
because it has to be at
the same time soft enough,
but also engaged enough
that you can actually feel
something. And so, you
know, see what it feels like
when other students have
their hands on you and
the differences between
them. And then the difference
between that and when
the instructor comes over
and puts their hands on
you. And then as it's your
turn and you've got to
try and find your contact,
you'll have some
knowledge. And that
really will go a
long way. And I can't
encourage you that
strongly enough.
When Dr. Wales taught me,
you know, she was long
retired, I would just go to
her house and we would talk
in the morning and then
she'd say, okay, it's time
for the demonstration. And
she'd lay me down and start
treating me and telling
me, okay, I'm doing this
and I'm doing that. And I
had to learn how to feel that
in my own body. And boy,
I could tell you, there's
really nothing and harder
for me to learn, but it
really changed the way I
understood things. So there's
value there. So he continued
his studies and ultimately
discovered motion, a
regular pattern of motion.
And within that, he
identified kind of five
separate components or
again, phenomena, because
he didn't deduce them.
He observed them.
And so the totality,
the overall motion that
he felt, he called the
primary respiratory
mechanism, back to
that initial thought of
design for motion, a
respiratory mechanism,
and also to reflect his
understanding of it.
and then we'll look at
each of those components
separately to understand
their role and to get insight
into his view of structure
function and osteopathy.
Ultimately,
you know, we can talk
about this, but I think the
key to osteopathy goes
on in the lab and really
learning how to feel it,
And it is not easy to feel,
but I will tell you that
for those of you that want
to practice osteopathic
work in your practices,
learning to sense the
primary respiratory mechanism
and to be able to observe
motion that is that
subtle is not only important
clinically, but critical
in your skills development.
So it is, as I will
tell you, it is absolutely
worth the time and it will
take time outside of
class in order to do that.
And then as we go through
his work, I will look at
some of the definitions of
words. Dr. Sutherland was
incredibly thoughtful about
his word choice. And so
as you read, and I do encourage
you to read, you know,
his writings, that just
if you come across a term
or a phrase and you don't
know what he's talking about,
you know, take some of
those words and look up the
dictionary definitions,
because he was using those.
Ann used to say that
anytime he wrote a
lecture, he had Webster's
Dictionary on the
table, and he'd often
look up words when he
was trying to find the
words that he needed.
Okay, so looking at the
primary respiratory mechanism
then, we have those five
components or phenomena.
There's the motility of the
brain and spinal cord, the
fluctuation of the
cerebrospinal fluid, the potency
of the tide as being part
of that. He did consider
that the fundamental or most
important principle, the
mobility of the dural
membranes, the mobility of the
cranial bones, and then
the mobility of the sacrum.
So take it together.
In terms of clinical
applications, You know, you
have a container and
contents and the idea that
the container, the bones
and the membranes serve to
support the functioning
of the contents, the brain
and the fluid, and that
the change in the container
will influence the
function of the contents.
hopefully you'll learn
at some point about
scoliosis and when
scoliosis gets bad
the distortion can
actually impair cardiac and
pulmonary function I actually
had a patient come to me
recently with a pretty
big scoliosis and it she
finally got to the doctor
because she was getting short
of breath and and so yes
the distortions of the
of the cranium are smaller
but the brain is much
more sensitive. The space
is much more tightly packed.
So a distortion like you're
seeing here can really
be significant and really
interfere with function.
And I think this model,
you know, with learning
disabilities in children
and all sorts of cranial
type problems, like nervous
system type problems,
can be impacted, not
necessarily caused by somatic
dysfunction, but certainly
impacted and made much
worse. And so there's an
avenue for treatment there.
In terms of the overall
movement of the primary
respiratory mechanism,
it is a change in shape.
He called the overall
movement, because he considered
a respiratory mechanism,
there's an inhalation phase
and an exhalation phase.
It's an alternating movement,
and in that alternating
movement during that inhalation
or opening phase, you
have a widening of the
transverse diameter that is
balanced or equal by a reduction
in the AP diameter, and
you can't see it in this
picture, but also a reduction
of the vertical diameter.
And then exhalation
would be the opposite,
narrowing of the transverse,
lengthening of the AP,
and deepening of the
vertical diameter.
And this alternating shape,
what you might call as you
get that inhalation phase,
like a swelling or expansile
phase, because that's
what it feels like, you'll
feel that everywhere in the
body. And I've come to view
the primary respiratory
mechanism as a total body
action that is involved
with physiology everywhere.
Remembering that fluid is
the fundamental principle. I
believe it does influence
our fluids. So we will get to
that if I can get through
this. So Dr. Wales used to
say, well, doctors still
called it osteopathy because
you start with the bones.
So we'll start there, the
mobility of the cranial
bones. And here it's looking
at the structure function.
But before we look at that,
you know, just the idea of
can there actually be
motion between the bones of
the head? And it's very
interesting that There is
a fair amount of study that
supports the idea that,
A, sutures don't close
during life, and that, B,
motion is permitted between
them. And then once you
get over that hump, then
you can start looking at
the design of those sutures
and the motion that they
accommodate, details that
will help you when that
suture becomes strained in
the same way that you need
to know the anatomy, which
way do the facets face,
and all that stuff in
order to really precisely
treat dysfunctions outside
and elsewhere in the body.
So obviously, no
one's going to argue
that sutures are
closed at birth.
Actually, there are no
sutures. The bones have
spaces between them.
We work in the nursery.
Every baby has motion
in their head. Most of
them have a very good
motion in their head.
And so those sutures
develop with that motion in
place. And so they develop in
such a way as to accommodate
that motion, because
the motion is very much
a part of the drive of
their development, which is
one of the reasons it's
so crucial to treat babies
and young children, because
you want that motion to
be normal, so development
goes normally. If you have
a birth strain that you
get at 10 years old even.
And the motion that
drove the development
of structure was
quite abnormal.
Reversing that is nearly
impossible. But at birth, it
sometimes can be a treatment
or two, something very
simple. And so that structure
-function relationship
really starts with the
development of those sutural
designs and beveling. And so
now you get an adult skull
and you can study those
sutures and you can say, oh,
well, this design is to
accommodate this kind of
motion. So here's the
motion that's present
there. And that was kind
of the early courses was
40 years of that, 40
hours of that before you
could get into the lab
and start feeling things.
So still, I believe the
single most important source
of anatomy is British
Grey's Anatomy. And they
use still a study by a
guy named Pritchard, this
picture, which is from
Grey's Anatomy and was from
Pritchard's study, and it's
the design of the suture.
And Pritchard, when
he finished his study,
he said, you know, it's
clear that, A, sutures don't
even fully form until
the late 20s. And if they
close after that, it's
very, very slowly. You know,
arguably, you could say
that the slow closing of a
suture over a lifetime
isn't all that dissimilar to
arthritic changes, where
all joint spaces narrow over
our lifetimes, and we move
less as we get older. But
even if your knee is bone
on bone, it still moves.
And likewise, there's
plenty of studies on
middle-aged and later
cadaveric specimens that
show evidence that
sutures are not closed.
And in his conclusion,
Pritchard said, you know, these
are obviously designed to
resist large forces, which
is what most anatomical
texts will sit on. Well, of
course, these sutures have
to close so that the cranium
can protect the brain. But
even with small movements
permitted, it still protects
the brain. Arguably, it
does so better because it's
more resilient and still
serve that protection while
it permits small movements.
So you can look for signs
that sutures are not closed.
Here's a neurovascular
bundle moving through a
suture. So if there's no,
you know, if the sutures
ossify, those will be
obliterated. And there's
plenty of studies
showing things like that,
showing sutural
ligaments still in place.
So that's something that if
you really don't believe,
I would encourage you to
go into the research and
look and see what's there.
And you really won't find
any true evidence that
sutures do fully ossify, and
you'll find plenty of evidence
that they in fact don't.
So yes, motion is possible.
So if you get over
that hump now, we can
start to look at that
structure function
relationship. So
remembering that, so this
is the parietals, the
parietal bones here.
there's my arrow, there's
my parietal bones, there
is the interdigitation of
the sagittal suture. So
to mimic what this does,
remembering that those
parietal bones have to swing
open during that inhalation
phase. If you just
interdigitate your fingers,
like the old, you know,
church and steeple little
game, anyway, interdigitate
your fingers and then
widen and narrow your
palms and see that that
inner digitation very similar
to the sagittal suture
accommodates exactly what
motion has to happen in those
parietal bones. And so a
serrated type of suture
accommodates a rocking motion
like that and perfectly
designed for that. And you can
see those inner digitations
here. If I now look to the
side where that increasing
transverse diameter, here
again, here's the side of
the parietal bone. Here's
the top of the temporal bone.
There, it's just a kind
of broadly overlapping.
They call this a squamous
type suture, which
allows kind of gliding,
or in this case, sort of
an expansion so that as
that transverse diameter
widens, it'll allow
that parietal temporal
to sort of expand a little
to accommodate that.
And so again,
structure and function,
there's the design.
Those are some obvious
ones. And if you
come take one of our
cranial courses, you
will get inundated with
lots of these details
that will become
critical when we get to
the tables and look to
treat some of these
areas. And then some broad
strokes about the
movement of the bones.
Dr. Sutherland made a
very big distinction
between the midline
bones, the bones of the
cranial base, and the
paired bones. All of
the midline bones are
formed in cartilage.
So this is, you know,
mesenchyme that
gets condensed into
cartilage and then
ossifies the bone.
This is looking from the
top. Here's the occiput.
Here's the sphenoid.
We would include the
petrous temporal. It's
the only paired bone that
is part of the base up
in front, the ethmoid.
And these bones undergo what
we call flexion extension.
The paired bones are the
ones that increase that
transverse diameter, and
they'll undergo external and
internal rotation. So those
terms going along. And
ultimately, Dr. Sutherland
would say that a true
articular mobility would occur
in the base, accommodated
by the movement of the
vault. So the fundamental or
primary dysfunctions would
be in the cranial base.
Those are very challenging
to work on and then
accommodated by the ones
in the vault. And treatment
of the base ultimately
will give you often
a more profound result
than would sort of staying
out on the periphery and
working in the vault,
parietals and frontals
and so forth. So the
movement of those midline
bones, so here we're
looking from the side,
we have the occiput, the
sphenoid, the ethmoid,
and the vomer as part of
the face. They all move
about transverse axes.
Those transverse axes,
those movements are
called flexion
extension the same way a
vertebra, when it moves
around a transverse
axis, undergoes
flexion and extension.
And all of these
bones move opposite so
that you get a kind
of a gear-like so that
during that flexion
phase or inhalation
phase, which is what
we're showing here,
this sphenobasilar junction
will move upwards. And that
upward movement of the
sphenobasilar junction,
remembering that the vertical
diameter is reduced, so that
sort of is where you find
that. and here you can see
that this is occiput and
sphenoid and then that
inhalation or flexion phase
that sphenobasical junction
moves upwards and extension
it moves downward so midline
bones transverse axes flexion
in the inhalation phase
extension during the
exhalation phase, the paired
bones now, looking at those
paired bones, they're going
to be the ones that increase
the transverse diameter.
And so the movement of those
paired bones will be called
external rotation when
they widen during the
inhalation phase and
internal rotation when they
narrow during the
exhalation phase. And so
inhalation phase, flexion
of the midline bones,
external rotation of the
paired bones, exhalation phase,
extension of the midline bones,
internal rotation of the
paired bones. And ultimately,
we have that increasing
transverse diameter
balanced by the reducing
AP and vertical diameters.
And so understanding
the primary respiratory
mechanism as a change in
shape, but not volume. And
that's important when we
get to the fluids, because
if you change volume,
you displace fluid and
fluid is not displaced.
It's simply moved back and
forth. So now let's quickly
look at the membranes.
And again, going back to
that concept of a ligamentous
articular mechanism. In
describing spinal lesions,
I refer to the term ligamentous
articular strain and
for the cranium membranous
articular strain because
the articulations and the
ligaments function as a
single unit, a ligamentous
articular or membranous
articular mechanism. So in the
cranium, we're then looking
at a membranous articular
mechanism with ultimately
the function of the
membranes then being guiding
and limiting the motion of
the bones. And here again,
that concept of a ligamentous
articular mechanism,
the interosseous membrane
in the cranium that
holds the bones of the
cranium together and
allows a certain range of
movement at the joints.
That interosseous membrane
is the dura mater.
And then this from Anne being
a hugely important concept
that the ligamentous articular
mechanism is essentially
a concept of the skeleton,
the bones and the membranes
that bind them, as
being independent of the
neuromuscular system that moves
it voluntarily. And so as a
separate organ system or
independent mechanical
system, then it's not moved
by voluntary movement.
It's moved by involuntary
action. And so that really,
in many ways, in my mind,
came from the development of
the cranial concept, where
one of the things Dr.
Sutherland says early on is,
you know as soon as I realized
that motion was present I
looked for the muscles that
crossed the joints and you'll
see muscles that attach
to the head and go elsewhere
but no muscles that go
from one bone to the other to
move it like the rotatories
and inner transversary I do
for intersegmental motion
in the spine and so since
there was no possibility of
voluntary movement that
brought him into the realm of
involuntary action, which
I think is very much a part
of the discovery of the
primary respiratory mechanism
and involuntary physiological
movement in the cranium.
So as we look at the
membranes and their role
then, they would be
to guide and limit the
motion of the cranial
bones. And to do so, then
they will need to
attach to each of the
cranial bones. We'll look
at those attachments.
And ultimately, when you
examine babies and little
ones, remember that the
bones are soft and there's no
articulations between them.
And so then the membranes
really serve a functional
role of stability, maintaining
shape and stability. And
a lot of the mechanical
problems in babies are membranous
in their origin. So when
he was talking about how
the membranes or ligaments
guide and limit motion,
he introduced the concept
of reciprocal tension. So
there's a couple of simple
ways. And again, the
concepts are the same,
whether you're in the head
or in the body, it just gets
a little more complex
in the head. And so here
we have a reciprocal tension
membrane in the forearm.
So here you can see
fibers in this direction,
here you can see fibers
in this direction. And so
reciprocal tension means
that I've got motion in
different directions, and
I've got fibers oriented in
those directions to help
limit. And so this is
something that you see in
a lot of different places.
Here's another reciprocal
tension ligament system
now. This is the
clavicle coming into the
manubrium and first rib.
And you see the ligaments,
you know, they just look
like a big bundle of
ligaments. When you dig in,
you can see this direction
and you can see this
direction perpendicular,
able to then directly
limit movement in opposing
directions because
they're perpendicular to
one another at that
sternoclavicular joint. So
that would be a reciprocal
tension ligament.
When we get to the cranium
then, now we've got a
modified sphere. And so
now instead of kind of
two-plane motion, we've
got three-plane motion.
And so those perpendicular
fibers now have to be in
three planes. So in the
AP plane or sagittal
plane, we have the falc
cerebri, and in the transverse
plane, the tentorium
cerebelli. And that was
really what Dr. Sutherland
described as the
reciprocal tension membrane,
the falcs and the tent.
Again, Dr. Sutherland was
a very logical thinker.
So if I'm going to
specifically guide and
limit motion of the bones
in relation to one another,
I need an attachment
to every one of them.
So starting in the front
here, we have attachment
to the ethmoid,
attachment to the frontal,
attachment to the parietals,
coming to the back.
Here, I'm hoping you can
see my arrow attachment
to the occiput, and then
here is where it adjoins
the tent, attaching
again to occiput, coming
around to temporal. This
is the petrous temporal,
and then finally ending
up on the sphenoid.
And so another concept
that he included was the
idea that if the membranes
are going to move the
bones, they need power.
And the power in movement
comes from leverage or a
lever, and that lever has to
have a fulcrum. And so
he described a fulcrum
within this primary respiratory
mechanism as somewhere
where the fulks and
tent adjoin one another,
which is, of course, the
area of the straight sinus.
And, you know, fulcrums
in diagnosis and treatment
are important. They're
still points around
which motion occurs. And
if you can identify them,
you can use them and
sometimes make your treatments
just much more powerful. So
that's why I included it.
And then finally, we have
what's called the core link,
or the fact that attaching
firmly at foramen magnum
as the lowest point of
cranial dura, that dura
continues as the wrapping of
the spinal cord and spinal
dura, which has firm
attachments at C2, C3, and then
falls relatively free
until it has, again, a firm
attachment at S2. And so that
sort of connection between
the foramen magnum at
the top and the sacrum at
the bottom brings the sacrum
into being part of the
primary respiratory mechanism.
It can't move unless
the sacrum moves between the
ilia. And so, at the very
least, the sacrum is part
of your cranial concept.
And excluding treatment
of the pelvis in someone
who, let's say, has a
bad head injury, and
you want to treat the
cranium, would be a
terrible mistake. If the
sacrum is really bound
up, that head is not
going to open up and move.
And so, part of his cranial
concept, whether you
want to consider the movement
of the sacrum, just one
of the movement of the
bones or as a separate,
sometimes it was listed
separately, just to sort of
emphasize the sacrum as an
important component. And
then the movement, he
described it like a sickle. A
sickle is like the the
scythe, where it's a blade
that curves more than 180
degrees. And so as it swings
forward, as you swing that
forward from the back,
the front of it turns on
itself and actually moves
inward. And so you can see
that and how that's going
to sort of guide and limit
that overall change in
AP diameter that occurs
during that inhalation
phase. And the tent also
kind of like a sickle, also
as arcing around in its
attachment to the sphenoid.
And the idea as a separate
component is that you
can have dysfunction that is
primarily in the membranes,
the same way in the body,
you can have fascial
strains. They're longer
strains, strains that are
more than just across a
single joint. They often will
extend a great distance.
And learning to identify
this, remember those
components are all observed,
learning to kind of
distinguish a membranous or
fascial strain from the
articular strains that occur
at either end of that
fascial strain can really
expand your diagnostic and
treatment capabilities.
Movement of the brain
and spinal cord,
we'll look briefly
at that movement.
And just to give you the
thought that this also is
an area where there is the
possibility for dysfunction.
And so a dysfunction of
the brain, I see pretty
commonly in traumatic brain
injuries. And yes, treating
the bones and membranes
to improve function,
because if you get a concussion
bad enough to give you
a traumatic brain injury,
that is going to have a
huge impact on the bones and
the membranes. but sometimes
it's the motility of
the brain that's a big
component. And if you can't
identify that in treatment
and treat it, you don't
entirely help your patient.
And so motility, again, he
chose that term. The bones
and membranes have mobility,
so they need to be moved.
Motility is capable of
moving itself. And so he did
think there was motion that
originated from the brain.
He did not consider it
the drive of the primary
respiratory mechanism that
is in the fluid, which
we're about to get to. And
then when he described the
nervous system, he'd look
at embryology because
the movement of the nervous
system can be seen from
its development. So this
is early development. The
nervous system is really
just a tube, and then it
grows this bud that's
going to become our brain.
And that tube elongates,
but that bud at the top
dips down. and you can see
here it dips down quite
a bit before it then these
cortical buds that are
going to become our cortex
come off and those are
going to coil so here you
see the cortex starting to
develop and it kind of
coils in this picture here
it is now really coiling
around um and um and here's
that uh directionality
so the neural tube comes
up dips down and then the
cortex comes out in coils
and that sort of coiling
and uncoiling is the
motion of the um of the
neural tube uh to to sort of
see it um in in function
again uh lengthening uh
dipping down and then a
coiling out of the cortex.
And you can see that in the
shape of the ventricles.
Here's the center of
the neural tube comes up
and I lost my arrow,
kind of coils down. And
then this lateral ventricle
would be that coiling
or uncoiling of the
cortex as it develops.
And so during inhalation
phase, this is going to coil.
It's going to get, the
spinal cord's going to lift
like a tadpole's tail,
and this is going to coil
getting kind of shorter
and fatter, the same shape
change that you get in the
bones and the membranes. And
then during exhalation,
it would be the opposite.
And then finally, we come
to the fluctuation of
the cerebrospinal fluid,
the potency of the tide,
that being A, because
there's a physiological
potency, and B, because
this is really what he
thought was driving
the primary respiratory
mechanism, he would say,
as the thing that makes it
move. So we'll start with
the concept of fluctuation
and why it's so important,
remembering that
in the BLT, I kind of
brought up the thought
that the goal of an
osteopathic treatment is to
promote the interchange
of fluid. So let's kind
of take a look at the
concept of fluctuation.
Remember that this is
something that happens
everywhere in the body
and why it's so important.
So fluctuation differs
from circulation.
Circulation is the
movement of fluid
into a place and
out of the place.
Fluctuation, again, no
change in volume, so you
don't displace the fluid,
you just kind of move
it back and forth. He
likened that movement to
the movement of the tide,
which moves the ocean
water kind of back and
forth in a regular rhythm.
And I'm going to introduce
the idea to you that
circulation is not
sufficient for exchange,
that sort of
interchange that needs
to happen with every
cell in our body.
Every cell in our body
needs to bring in nutrients,
needs to bring in oxygen,
and needs to get rid of
waste and carbon dioxide.
And that circulation brings
the supply to the general
area, but it's fluctuation
that's going to really
determine what's happening
at that interstitial space,
the microcirculation,
if you will. So the CSF
does have a circulation,
fluid comes in at the
choroid plexus, and
then will exit at the
arachnoid granulation.
This is not sufficient
for all the functions
of the CSF. And so we
can look at this concept
of fluctuation. It
is a general concept,
heart, vascular
system, capillary beds,
interstitium with cellular
exchange, and then
we'll look at this from
the other side. This
is a lymphatic vessel,
but this is really
where exchange is going
to be. And ultimately,
the pressure in the
interstitium is negative.
And so fluids will not
move themselves when
faced with a negative
interstitial pressure.
And so circulation would
bring some fluid in. But
here where exchange is
occurring, there would be
stasis. unless you have some
sort of action to create
that fluctuation. I look
at the idea of a bathtub.
And if you had a drip at
the faucet on one end,
bringing fluid in and a
drip at the drain, the
exact same rate at the
other end, taking fluid
away, and you poured
some particulates into
that tub, it would all
settle into the bottom.
But if you could get a hand
in that tub and just create
a little action in that
water, moving it back and
forth, now that water
will stay mixed. All those
particulates will stay mixed.
And so for all the cells that
are trying to live in that
tub, now there's continuously
changing concentration
gradients, facilitating
cellular exchange. And so
that's the idea, the concept
of an interstitial mechanism
based in fluid fluctuation
necessary for cellular
exchange functioning with
the forces of circulation.
And that really, to me,
is part of the potency of
this primary respiratory
mechanism as you feel it
everywhere in the body. The
idea of, is there an environment
here with the presence
of a primary respiratory
mechanism that promotes
exchange? Or is there stasis
that now really limits the
ability of those cells to
exchange? And how can any
tissue respond to any kind
of disease or challenge if
it's not having effective
cellular exchange in that
tissue. And so this is such
a fundamental principle.
And so then comes the question,
well, what makes
that fluid move then?
And this is what he said
about it. Dr. Whale said
he was looking straight at
her when he said, you know,
within that cerebrospinal
fluid, there's an
invisible element that I refer
to as the breath of life.
I want you to visualize
this breath of life as a
fluid within the fluid,
something that does not mix,
something that has
potency as the thing that
makes it move. So he's
calling the action that
creates that fluctuation,
the breath of life.
And then, is it really
necessary to know
what makes the fluid
move? Apparently, she
asked him constantly
throughout all of
her time, well, what
makes the fluid move?
And so, finally, in one of
her last visits to him, he
said, I don't know. And so,
you know, it's there. You
can learn how to feel it.
So is it really necessary
to know what makes that
fluid move? So putting this
all together, we have a
container and its contents. We
have mobility of the bones
and the membranes, which
guide and limit that mobility,
including the sacrum,
supporting the motility of
the brain and spinal cord,
which you'll find abnormal
both in post concussion
syndromes and head injuries,
learning problems, all kinds
of problems that show up
as nervous system or brain
dysfunction and that critical
fluctuation of fluid,
something that's
critical everywhere
in the body and the
presence or absence
of this primary
respiratory mechanism
everywhere in the body is
something that you can use
in diagnosis and treatment.
Motility of the neural tube
following the path of development,
coiling and uncoiling,
synchronous with the primary
respiratory mechanism
and in the same shape change,
the fluctuation of the
CSF, the fundamental principle,
a to-and-fro movement
that works with circulation
to promote interchange,
particularly at the cellular
level or microcirculation,
the mobility of the dural
membranes, guiding and
limiting the movement of
the bones in that concept of
a ligamentous articular or
membranous articular mechanism,
and the movement of those
membranes are arcing.
He likened it to a sickle
operating from a fulcrum,
and then finally the
mobility of the bones with
all of the midline bones
moving about a transverse
axis into flexion and
extension, flexion during the
inhalation phase, extension
during the exhalation
phase, and the paired
bones then also going under
external rotation and internal
rotation also with the
inhalation and exhalation
phases. Put it all together,
you get a change in shape
but not volume during
inhalation, a widening of
the transverse diameter
accompanied by a narrowing
of the AP and vertical
diameters and reverse
during the exhalation phase.
And if you ever want
to remember those shape
changes, just remember
that inhalation phase is
going to be Ernie and
exhalation phase will be
BERT and nobody can
forget those two shapes.
So the cranial concept
is really a part
of the osteopathic
concept. In order to
really study it, you
have to learn how to
feel it. That is going
to be the hard part.
It was discovered by Dr.
Sutherland in the head, but
is something that you can
find everywhere in the body
and really is tied to overall
physiological functioning
with those five components,
mobility of bones and
membranes, motility of the
neural tube, fluctuation of
the fluid. And it's
something that you can use to
diagnose details of somatic
dysfunction, but also kind of
gives you an idea of the
overall health of the body.